<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://csaund.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://csaund.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-17T08:06:52-04:00</updated><id>https://csaund.github.io/</id><title type="html">Carolyn Saund</title><subtitle>PhD Student at University of Glasgow</subtitle><author><name>Carolyn Saund</name><email>carolyn.saund@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Cancel Culture Doesn’t Exist, Followup</title><link href="https://csaund.github.io/blog/cancelculture_2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cancel Culture Doesn't Exist, Followup" /><published>2021-03-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-03-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://csaund.github.io/blog/blog-post-16</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://csaund.github.io/blog/cancelculture_2/">&lt;p&gt;Thanks all for the engagement on my last post about “cancel culture” (I’m not an #influencer or anything, I just like discussion). In light of a few points that were raised, I’ve written a follow-up that I think clarifies some of my position, incorporates some peoples’ comments, and speaks more directly to some folks’ concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to “cancel culture,” it seems like there are three related but distinct situations that come up: celebrities, ideas (academics), and individual people (witch hunts). Last time I talked a lot about how apologies and personal growth seem to completely mitigate bad behavior by celebrities. Here I’ll be talking about the latter issues. And, I maintain and will tie in how the phrase “cancel culture” is weaponized to sow fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll talk first about the “de-platforming” of particular academics. Largely, my stance on this is the same as in my last post: we don’t owe anybody a platform. Academic spaces are being characterized as “intolerant,” but I think the only thing that has stopped being tolerated is intolerance and exclusive focus on the white/male/hetero/able-bodied/neurotypical/etc perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[[I won’t talk here about views that espouse tolerance vs. intolerance i.e. I don’t want to have the discussion here which equates de-platforming a speaker whose platform is racial equality vs. whose platform is explicit white superiority, and I also don’t want to talk about niche oppressive communities that explicitly disallow outside information]]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, I would be upset if I found out that part of my conference fees went to paying for a keynote from someone whose platform is “parents should be able to euthanize disabled infants,” because I find that view remarkably out-of-touch with current cultural discussions that have us talking so much more about quality of life for disabled people who have been historically neglected, and I feel like that person hasn’t examined their views since the 70s and I don’t want my money going to them. I would consider not attending a conference if that conference were paying that person. That person’s views run contrary to my values, and I don’t want to support them, and I have absolutely no obligation to. Likewise, a group of people representing an organization have no obligation to support views that run counter to their core values. Or, for a more capitalistic reason, would lose money from supporting that person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, people aren’t banned from coming to events to learn or share their ideas in small circles, or participating in online forums or reading journals. They are banned from getting paid to speak and propagate their views to specific in-person audiences. They aren’t censored on twitter, often are held up as shining examples of “free speech,” and defended by staunch purists, and overwhelmingly they aren’t stopped from publishing, either privately or in journals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, because they had huge platforms to begin with, their voice booms out of their cultural microphone when they say “what a shame, the liberals are being closed-minded,” when in fact they are simply not listening or responding to the valid concerns of new and changing cultural perspectives. They complain they are being “cancelled,” when in fact they are just being held accountable, by a wide audience, perhaps for the first time. Without gaslighting here, to them I would say that it is common among arguments to say “you’re not listening to me” when in fact you are not listening to them, either. De-platforming is enforcing social accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, witch hunts DO happen. I’m going to spell this out at the top: harassment is not ok – not even for genuinely bad people – and de-platforming and holding others accountable is completely different from harassment. The term “cancel culture” aims to equate the two, and is strategically designed and deployed to paint a picture where holding people accountable is the same as harassing them. Harassment happens, and that is bad. Harassment is not the same as holding people accountable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, witch hunts either happen because of misinformation and perhaps deliberately lying about the contents of someone’s statements (as in the Rebecca Tuvel case), or because of person-to-person miscommunication (the Smith college case). A common denominator in these cases, and I suspect many other “witch hunt,” situations, is that some overseeing, moderating party completely failed to moderate and scapegoated the person who ended up being unfairly characterized, blamed, harassed, etc. They may have failed to provide adequate support to an aggrieved person who then went on to start the witch hunt, or failed to provide any platform at all to defend the person being targeted. The anger of a witch hunt is often righteous, although I agree it can be misdirected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witch hunts also aren’t new. Obviously the etymology of the word hints to society’s long history of working off of incomplete or incorrect facts. Witch hunts also are absolutely, 100% not distinct to one political ideology, or even one field. Highlighting witch hunts is a fear-mongering tactic that, again, absolutely works because humans are completely attuned to respond to social threats, especially in the current global context. The political right in the US absolutely dominates at using this term, from Trump declaring the Meuller investigation “the greatest witch hunt in American history” (and having no consequences from the investigation supports this claim), to the RNC calling to “STOP THE WITCH HUNT” in the Kavanaugh hearing (again, his ascension to the SCOTUS backs up this claim). Similarly, #MeToo is labeled a “feminist witch hunt,” and lots and lots and lots of men I know feel like they must look over their shoulder in case they “have ever done anything wrong.” US conservatives have convinced the public, regardless of where you stand on these issues, that witch hunts happen, that they are meritless, and that they target innocent men. And they use the term “cancel culture,” to equate social accountability to witch hunts and unmerited harassment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the fear of one day being the target of a witch hunt, I reiterate this: it is very difficult to paint a nasty caricature of someone who genuinely wants to understand another’s position. If I feel I am unfairly characterized for an innocent mistake, it is likely that either a miscommunication has occurred, or I have unknowingly made an innocent mistake. In either case, the first step towards de-escalation is listening to the aggrieved party – either to see if we’re working on the same facts (“she called the police” when in fact I did not) or if I could have misstepped (“she racially profiled me,” you know what, that is possible). Psychologically, when someone feels heard, they are more willing to listen and less likely to dehumanize the person listening to them. Furthermore, if my institution throws me under the bus, I also hope I’ll have the wherewithal to hold them accountable as well (“Why didn’t you protect me from harassment? Why is there no policy against posting personal information?”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, on that, I want to make a note that is extremely important for me personally. Emotion does not run counter to logic. Emotion is a mitigating factor that affects many bodily and cognitive processes. It does not affect our ability to see facts, but rather influences which facts we pay attention to. If you ask me in a heightened emotional state what’s an equal split of $100 between two, I will always say $50. However, depending on the facts I have, that is very different from what I might see as a &lt;em&gt;fair&lt;/em&gt; split. If you owe me $10 from before, I might say “actually just give me the $10 you owe me now and give me $60,” but you might say “that has nothing to do with this, let’s split this 50/50 and I’ll still owe you $10.” If we’re on good terms, that might be fine. But if you just insulted me, I might insist that actually it’s &lt;em&gt;fair&lt;/em&gt; for me to get the $60 now. With this example, it’s easier to see how many miscommunications between the left and right are based not only on working with different facts as ground truth, but also how heightened emotional states and hurt feelings play into escalating situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phrase “cancel culture” (and more generally, “Culture Wars”) is designed to get people into heightened emotional states – to get you to feel like YOU, YOU PERSONALLY, are being attacked for having done nothing wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I say “cancel culture isn’t real,” THAT is what I mean. “Cancel culture” is a boogieman, and if the term scares you, the tactic is working. This isn’t an insult at all – social fear is natural, it is everywhere, and it is being explicitly cultivated by malevolent actors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real changes are afoot, though. Equality and equity are uncomfortable for those who flourish under the status quo, so it will take time to adjust to new norms. There will be growing pains where we all reconcile “what is equal” with “what is fair.” Social media literacy is weird and bad and has led to unjustified harassment, and we all bear responsibility for doing due-diligence on issues that matter to us and teaching those around us how to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, we have to make philosophical peace with what we believe we owe to ourselves, what we owe to others, and what others owe to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My take on this is remarkably unbalanced: that I owe myself a right to be treated fairly and respectfully and to be taken seriously, and a right to protect myself; I owe others a right to be protected and heard, up until they violate the right of others to be protected; others owe me nothing, and their kindness is a nice bonus and a choice that they actively make for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explicitizing this has been a useful exercise for me in understanding why I feel the way I do about this issue. I hope it’s a useful exercise for you, too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Carolyn Saund</name><email>carolyn.saund@gmail.com</email></author><category term="cancel culture" /><category term="politics" /><category term="social justice" /><summary type="html">Thanks all for the engagement on my last post about “cancel culture” (I’m not an #influencer or anything, I just like discussion). In light of a few points that were raised, I’ve written a follow-up that I think clarifies some of my position, incorporates some peoples’ comments, and speaks more directly to some folks’ concerns.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cancel Culture Doesn’t Exist</title><link href="https://csaund.github.io/blog/cancelculture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cancel Culture Doesn't Exist" /><published>2021-03-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://csaund.github.io/blog/blog-post-15</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://csaund.github.io/blog/cancelculture/">&lt;p&gt;Hey y’all, back atcha with another Long post about Cancel Culture, because it seems like it’s an issue that effectively and efficiently sews divide in folks across the spectrum in a way that is surprising and frankly quite frightening. Please engage if you feel moved to, I promise to moderate conversations on this post to be civil and mutually respectful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, “Cancel Culture” is a conservative propaganda tactic designed to appeal to “logic,” and specifically targets men and white folks to make it seem like the past was better than it was, and that your way of life is being attacked, and that one day the “Woke Mob” will come for you. It is a fallacy that pretends to reduce liberal arguments for inclusivity and equity ad absurdism to complete nonsense. It preys on very normal fears of being attacked, of being innocently misunderstood and sentenced to ostracism for doing something someone doesn’t even know they did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conservative mindsets may claim that Cancel Culture is “being PC gone too far,” and that “people are too afraid to have fun or make a joke anymore because they might get cancelled.” In this post, I will explain how that is simply not the case, and why the words “Cancel Culture” are carefully calculated to scare you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; To explain my view of “Cancel Culture,” I use the playground example. If you see two five-year-olds on the playground and one says to the other “I want to play with you,” and the other says back “No, you were mean to my friends yesterday, I think you’re mean, I don’t want to play with you” and the first one starts crying, it’s pretty natural to say “well that’s fair enough, they shouldn’t have been mean in the first place and now they got what’s coming.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, think of it like this: cancel culture is literally just boycotting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems uncontentious to say that sometimes boycotting stuff is good. Boycotts are one of the few ways that mass groups of people can have a say over societal issues (another is voting). Boycotts were huge tools during the civil rights movements, for example. Nowadays, it seems like the right would say “the Montgomery bus system has been CANCELLED.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cancelling someone, simply put, is to stop giving support to someone. But some folks even on the political left will say that “Cancel Culture has gone too far” and that “once you’re cancelled there’s no coming back.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll handle these points with the example of Aziz Ansari. Ansari was famously accused of what we would nowadays call sexual harassment bordering on assault, but what at the time I and many other women just thought of as a bad date with a pushy guy. Ansari was a beloved comedian, famously left-wing and feminist, when an expose was written by a woman who claimed he was insistent, unrelenting in his sexual advances towards her on a date. Despite his apology, overnight Ansari was cancelled. His TV show stopped running, his live shows were called off. He was out of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, I thought this was an example of “cancel culture gone too far.” Do I think his behavior was bad? Yeah, but I mean, it’s expected. C’mon, it’s a date, of course the guy’s gonna be pushy. But the more I discussed it, the more it dawned on me that actually, that is not ok. “Of course sometimes men make me feel unsafe” is in fact a terrible justification for why I should continue to support this man’s career.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then something funny happened. A year later he released another live show, and in it, he apologized again. He apologized to the woman again, and he apologized genuinely. As a woman who has had many pushy guys make me feel unsafe (“because that’s just how it is”), I felt like he apologized to me. He expressed that he was scared, that he’s grateful for the redemption arc he has been given, and that he vows to change his behavior in the future, because before it was not ok. Because, again, just because something is normalized does not make it ok.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot say this enough. Just because something is normalized does not make it ok. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have many more examples of people who have been “cancelled,” and why their behavior has not been ok or why their situation is not an example of “cancel culture,” that I am happy to discuss, but would take too long here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; “Cancel culture” is an attempt to change social norms from being unnecessarily harmful to certain groups, to reflecting better versions of ourselves and our aspirations. It is a boycott on incivility and hatred and harassment and, yes, sometimes, just being a complete arse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the term “cancel culture” is being weaponized to scare you, but often those fears have incredibly shallow roots. Two topical examples from the US are great places to start – genderless Mr. Potato head and Dr. Seuss are both Fox News’ examples of “Cancel Culture.” In the former, a plastic potato that has always been sold with a male and female-presenting face is now being sold as a plastic potato. The conservative argument is “they’re taking away Mr. Potato head!” when that is just… not happening? I don’t know. I don’t know why they latched onto this one so hard. It’s a plastic toy potato that is continuing to be sold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Seuss Estate voluntarily decided to stop printing 6 books that have particularly egregious racist imagery. This is obviously not cancel culture, because there was no legal or social pressure for them to do so, and their reputation is fully intact. I will still be buying my nephew Oh The Places You’ll Go and The Lorax, because they’re great books with great messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Seuss is interesting because it opens a discussion on Book Banning. Some professed liberals say that Cancel Culture is basically leftist Book Banning. In fact, it is the opposite. Book Banning is functionally disallowing ideas to be spread from the top-down; some governing body decides a book contains imagery or ideology that they don’t want to propagate, so they outlaw the book. “Cancelling” (boycotting) is bottom-up, when a group of people with enough critical mass boycotts something, because the group decides that its own values conflict with the thing they’re boycotting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So then if “cancel culture” is just boycotting, why does the phrase even exist? And why is it so scary, and so pervasive, and so in-your-face? It’s because the right wing owns the meaning of the word, and owning meaning is dangerous. Its etymology is probably based on “rape culture” which was coined by liberals as it was highlighted as the danger it is in how casual misogyny and sexual harassment jokes were in the 90s/00s and before (have you rewatched Friends or How I Met Your Mother lately? Big Yikes). It’s reminiscent of attacks on “classic” pieces of media that, in retrospect, actually are really problematic, but at the time seemed fine. It’s essentially absolutely twisting progressive values (equality/the idea that maybe people shouldn’t be threatened by violence constantly) and throwing liberals words back at them, but in a sick mirror.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Cancel culture” cannot exist. If it were a thing, if it really existed, that would mean that people are entitled to your attention. But we know that is not the case. YOU can choose who to pay attention to. And, ultimately, you choose to be kind. You don’t HAVE to care about someone’s feelings. If somebody explains why words or actions hurt them, you don’t have to care about them, or change your behavior. But you do have to make peace with the fact that you are choosing to not care, and other people can see that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; The right-wing message is that one day, you will be cancelled. One day, the mob will turn on you for something you didn’t even know you did, and your life will be over, swiftly and without justice.  The opposite is true. One day, you may slip up and make a joke that is off-color, that makes fun of a marginalized or disenfranchised group, that uses a word that has been deemed uncouth (as the meaning of words does change over time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I am here to tell you that you will NOT be alienated or ostracized. You may be called out and embarrassed, which is imo quite rude, but more likely you’ll be called IN. Someone will tell you “hey it’s actually not cool to say that anymore for x y z reason,” or “dude that joke was actually making fun of this person,” and all you have to say, literally the only thing you have to do is say: “Oh, I didn’t know that. Thanks for telling me.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Woke Mob is a myth. Cancel Culture is a myth. It is a myth that is borne from fear of change and exacerbated by those who stand to profit from the status quo. Fear of change is a natural reaction that I myself have felt many, many times. I have felt attacked and like my sense of humor or my personality has been under threat, that people I love or thought I liked were mad at me for just being myself. But I have been humbled and I have grown from the many people with the patience to talk things through with me, and I am grateful because my friends WANT me to grow into a person I like more — who is more inclusive and makes fewer accidental gaffes, and whose actions reflect my values of empathy, inclusivity, and compassion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Carolyn Saund</name><email>carolyn.saund@gmail.com</email></author><category term="cancel culture" /><category term="politics" /><category term="social justice" /><summary type="html">Hey y’all, back atcha with another Long post about Cancel Culture, because it seems like it’s an issue that effectively and efficiently sews divide in folks across the spectrum in a way that is surprising and frankly quite frightening. Please engage if you feel moved to, I promise to moderate conversations on this post to be civil and mutually respectful.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Coronavirus Information</title><link href="https://csaund.github.io/blog/vaccine_information/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coronavirus Information" /><published>2020-12-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://csaund.github.io/blog/blog-post-17</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://csaund.github.io/blog/vaccine_information/">&lt;p&gt;Coronavirus vaccination information, for my friends who express concerns over how quickly the vaccine was developed, from a total lay-person-who-knows-a-bit-of-biology’s perspective. This is NOT written for anti-vaxxers, but for the many friends I’ve had who express skepticism at how quickly this vaccine was developed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(1) This became THE TOP PRIORITY for every big pharma company, basically overnight. This means there were huge funding boosts to this vaccine (because emergency), huge collaboration efforts, and huge promises of big payoffs ($$$ and fame) for being first. So, there was concentrated firepower straight from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(2) Development for this vaccine started BEFORE the virus existed, as it was hypothesized a novel SARS-CoV-2 virus would emerge and cause the havoc it has. I don’t know how or why this was hypothesized, bc I’m not a virologist, but I know that virology is a whole field of study and we know a bit about how viruses evolve so I’m sure someone has put two and two together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(3) The clinical trials for the vaccines have been expedited, not reduced. That is, MORE people have been allowed in trials SOONER, it is NOT the case that fewer people have been tested, but instead that more people (around 40,000 for Pfizer/BioNTech, 39,000 for moderna I believe) have been allowed to be tested sooner. Again, not necessarily with less paperwork; this is everybody’s TOP concern. There are zero competing interests – everybody wants the vaccine out ASAP. More here: https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-02416-z&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(4) The negative backlash of an ineffective or dangerous vaccine would far far far far far outweigh being first to the punch, so it is in nobody’s interest to cut any safety corners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(5) Side effects: All vaccines come with side effects (my left arm was out of commission for two days after a tetanus shot). Zero (0, zilnch, nada) serious side effects have occurred in any clinical trials. Some people feel crappy for a few days. Some even run a low fever. This is the same for all vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(6) “It’s a new type of vaccine”: Yes the mRNA is a new kind of vaccine, and one that could be more effective than any that have come before. I don’t claim to understand much, but my basic understanding is instead of a normal vaccine which injects a bit of “deactivated” virus for your body to “learn to fight off” itself, it actually injects mRNA which tells your cells to build a specific disease antigen (a signaller of the actual virus), which prepares your body to fight the actual virus when it encounters it. More here: https://www.phgfoundation.org/briefing/rna-vaccines. My takeaway is if you’re generally ok with vaccines that inject a bit of deactivated virus, this strikes me as a way safer and more intuitive method of inoculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(6.5) “I don’t know what’s in it”: You can look up what’s in most vaccines pretty easily, and the COVID vaccine wikipedia page is quite comprehensive: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/COVID-19_vaccine…. Also, we put things into our body all the time that we don’t know what’s in them. I have no idea how vitamins work, but I take a vitamin D tablet every day. Similarly, experts say it’s good for me to eat lots of vegetables and avoid soda, so I do. I have literally no idea what the body chemistry is, but I listen to experts on these counts so no reason not to keep consistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(7) “I’ll wait until other people get it to know it’s safe”: Ultimately, you are within your rights if you don’t want to get the vaccine. However, you have to accept that you are putting OTHERS at risk as well as yourself. It is beyond personal risk; just like you’re required to wear a seatbelt because you could be a danger to others, you are a danger to others if you do not protect yourself by getting vaccinated. If you DO refuse to get the vaccine “until it’s safe,” then I recommend you make a plan for WHEN you’ll get the vaccine. Once 60M people have had it? 100M? How will you account for the purposeful misinformation that some people will propagate around the vaccine? When you hear “vaccine horror stories,” how will you critically examine them, knowing some people actively want to scare you out of the vaccine?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, if you have questions or corrections to anything I’ve written, please comment or let me know. Nobody is going to tear you down for asking questions, and I know quite a lot of knowledgeable people I’m happy to tag if you want a literal expert opinion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Carolyn Saund</name><email>carolyn.saund@gmail.com</email></author><category term="coronavirus" /><category term="vaccine" /><category term="misinformation" /><summary type="html">Coronavirus vaccination information, for my friends who express concerns over how quickly the vaccine was developed, from a total lay-person-who-knows-a-bit-of-biology’s perspective. This is NOT written for anti-vaxxers, but for the many friends I’ve had who express skepticism at how quickly this vaccine was developed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Using Pronouns</title><link href="https://csaund.github.io/blog/using_pronouns/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using Pronouns" /><published>2020-12-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://csaund.github.io/blog/blog-post-18</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://csaund.github.io/blog/using_pronouns/">&lt;p&gt;I have some friends who I suspect might be confused by Elliot Page coming out. Specifically, when to use which pronouns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking cues from their post and acting credit updates, they probably wish to be referred to in the past has either he or they (even though they outwardly identified as female at the time). So it’s ok to say “I loved him in Juno.” If he posts something about wishing this to be different in the future, this can change! This confused me a lot at first, and from experience seems different for different people. But for now, HE starred in the 2004 classic I Downloaded A Ghost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He/they usually means he’s comfortable if you refer to him as EITHER he or they — you don’t have to switch for different grammar usages. If he posts something about wishing this to be different in the future, this can change! There’s a lot of reasons people allow multiple pronouns, but I won’t get into that here and I’m obvs not an expert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re trying to remember his name and can’t (“oooo who was that actor in that one movie, you know, the &lt;strong&gt;__&lt;/strong&gt; one”) it’s ok use trans as a descriptor. It’s not a dirty word, it is an adjective that varies from ok-because-we-need-to-normalize  to worn proudly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you slip up, don’t make a big fuss. Just correct quickly if you remember (or someone else does) and move on — “I once saw her, I mean him, at a festival!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pronouns are simultaneously kind of the least important but also most important thing. Yes, the way you treat individuals and the way you feel in your heart is most important. But respecting their transitions means really accepting who they are NOW, and in that sense, who they’ve always been. And that includes pronouns. (If you’ve ever referred to yourself in the wrong gender in Spanish/French/German, you know how funny people find it and consequently how much it MATTERS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;it’s ok and pretty normal for this to be a learning experience. You’re not going to get “cancelled” for trying to learn or asking clarifying questions! If you’re confused about why this matters or have more specific questions you can ask me, or google, or comment below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, I am learning as well, so if you have different experiences or know something I don’t about this (very likely) I’d welcome any and all feedback!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Carolyn Saund</name><email>carolyn.saund@gmail.com</email></author><category term="trans rights" /><category term="pronouns" /><category term="transgender" /><summary type="html">I have some friends who I suspect might be confused by Elliot Page coming out. Specifically, when to use which pronouns.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">‘Violence isn’t the answer’</title><link href="https://csaund.github.io/blog/political_violence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="'Violence isn't the answer'" /><published>2020-06-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://csaund.github.io/blog/blog-post-21</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://csaund.github.io/blog/political_violence/">&lt;p&gt;For Folks who think Racism exists and needs to be dealt with, But Violence Is Never The Answer. Longest so far, and with the fewest concrete sources. I can’t find many good statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regular ground rules. Peace, love, non-judgemental discussion. US-centric lens. Links to everything at the bottom. TW physical abuse/violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll start by being the first one to say that violence absolutely sucks. It is horrendous that violence is happening at “peaceful” protests. It is very, very sad that some small businesses have been destroyed in such a way that they may never recover, potentially putting a POC or a family out of business and into a desperate situation. And it is a complete travesty that occasionally, innocent bystanders are hurt and sometimes even actively targeted. Nobody likes that. Nobody is happy that buildings are burning and people are being hurt. It sucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will here share an article that was shared with me, describing an incident in which the statue of an abolitionist, unionist colonel (who died fighting for the Union in the Civil War) was torn down, and in which Democratic senator Tim Carpenter was assaulted by protestors after taking a video of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an obviously horrible incident, and one which I imagine those involved regret. So, we wonder, why did this happen? How did it comes to this? “Why can’t they protest peacefully?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer this we need a brief history lesson. Black Lives Matter (BLM) started in 2013 after the murder of Trayvon Martin (17) and subsequent acquittal of George Zimmerman. The organization (movement?) gained recognition after the Ferguson demonstrations following the shooting of Michael Brown in 2014 — the origin of the chant/slogan “Hands Up Don’t Shoot.” Since then, BLM has orgnanized thousands of protests across the country, including some that either disrupted my day or that I took part in in Boston between 2015-2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have been protesting peacefully since before the Ferguson riots, (2014) and before the Baltimore riots (2016). Peaceful demonstrations have flooded liberal cities before, and some smaller areas have suffered property damage from them in the past, and, critically, things are not changing nationwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can look at the data and say “more white people are being killed by police than black people” but I’m sure we all understand that because of demographic makeup of the US, proportionally that means far more black people are being harmed by police than white. I am pretty bad at statistics, but I believe this means that the way a Bayesian might explain this is “Given that a person is black, it is more likely for them to experience police violence.” Correct me if I’m wrong, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also say “but the trend is going down!” Which is fantastic, but that means in 2019 there were still 28 unarmed black folks killed by police. Why in the world is that number not 0? This also fails to account for incidents of police violence (not killings by police), as well as officer accountability (99% of incidents of police killing a black person resulted in no charges let alone a conviction).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, hopefully now we can sit on the common footing that police brutality against black folks IS a problem, and despite years of protest there has been no result (or at least not enough of one that addresses the systemic issues at hand).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will ignore the “what about MLK” argument and instead point to articles describing his arc towards nonviolent resistance (which began with violent resistance) and how his historical message is sometimes distorted for white comfort / “we’re past that now” rhetoric. There are dozens of articles on this but here’s the one I read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m gonna be honest and maybe a shitty liberal here and say it’s really hard to find exact facts and figures and examples of “riots” working for change on a systemic level. I know that in Ferguson the police chief changed and a bunch of new laws were passed. In Baltimore, from what I can tell, it looks like the riots led to a complete lack of policing and some very catty comments by the police departments [link] as well as a rise in violent crime. Looks like suffragettes used violence [link] and women have the right to vote, so that’s nice. And I can find plenty of academic experts who study civil disobedience and violence who suggest that property destruction is a good way to instigate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what my reading of these sources suggests to me, with a sympathetic view towards the protests:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A riot is the language of the unheard” is an understated MLK quote. When the media does not pay attention to your cause when you protest peacefully, if you break a few windows then suddenly it’s national (or international) news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire basis of MLK’s non-violence tactic was provoking openly (proudly) racist police chiefs and officers to attack them. It was this state-sanctioned violence against non-violent protestors that garnered widespread support for the Civil Rights movement. We see similar factors at play now, 50 years later, when we see the incredibly violent police response against overwhelmingly non-violent protests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is completely inappropriate to equate loss of life to loss of property. I really don’t think you’ll be able to convince me otherwise. People are protesting because they are in danger of being killed, and that fact has been demonstrated over and over and over and over. It is true that property is being destroyed and that is bad, but suggesting this is an eye for an eye is, in my personal opinion, almost wilfully ignorant. Lives are at stake. Businesses can recover but lives cannot be regained once lost. And for the businesses that struggle for years afterwards or that put someone into bankruptcy, I do feel sincerely sorry. It’s horrible that that happened. It really flippin’ sucks that it’s honestly like a trade-off between getting people to care about lost lives, and physical property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people talk about “violent” BLM protests, they are almost exclusively talking about property destruction. Statues being torn down, windows being smashed, “looting.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is impossible to prove who is doing the “looting.” I am sure there is at least one protestor who has stolen something, and at least one bystander taking advantage of the chaos. Neither side can prove how many protestors instigate breaking things and how many bystanders calculatedly carry hammers without relation to the cause. I’m sure we’ve all seen enough videos of people carrying BLM signs smashing windows, and people carrying BLM signs stopping others from entering stores and stealing things. We can’t interview people for their motivations, so I think the “looting” issue comes out in the wash. Protests lead to police being unable to access areas which leads to bad actors stealing stuff. This happens, but it seems like it’s impossible to prove who is responsible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that items are being stolen is NOT grounds to dismiss the hundreds of thousands of people who are peacefully demonstrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if it were entirely BLM protestors looting/causing damage (which I do not believe is true at all, but EVEN IF IT WERE), property destruction is how you get media attention. The smaller nationwide protests that have been going on for the last 7 years (and more before that, but 7 years since BLM began organising) have NOT resulted in large media attention, this has. Media attention is how you get recognition, is how you get followers, is how you get the sympathy of the group in power, is how you get change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell (granted, my google-fu is not great), BLM leadership has NEVER advocated for violence against individuals, except a few times where it seems like leaders have condoned (or at least explained?) violence in self-defence. This seems like a pretty peaceable position for a group that has been described as a terrorist organization by the highest leader in the land. So, while individuals may perpetrate bad actions, I think we must look to the tone of the leaders a movement if we want to characterise what that movement “stands for.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears that counter-protestors are way more likely to incite personal, human-targeted violence and actively come looking for a fight than BLM protests themselves. That’s the media I’m seeing, I can find absolutely ZERO statistics on it, but it’s certainly feeding a rising sense of fear-for-personal-safety that protestors may be experiencing. Any statistics on this are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And some more nuanced thoughts that have been more difficult for me to grapple with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mob mentality is real. I think a statue of a Good Guy™ was torn down in a frenzy. Same with the Ulysses Grant statue in SF. People have pent up anger and work themselves into a state where they do not think clearly and rigorously about how all their actions will be received and portrayed by the press. SF and Milwaukee obviously don’t have statues of confederate generals, but they do have statues of white dudes who were probably not the nicest guys (I cannot find any statistics on statues of people being slave owners/white/“bad” so I’m going with the general sentiment and tendency of society to idolise rich people, and that historically rich white people often have ill-gotten gains by today’s standards). In the heat of the moment, I think it makes sense to assume the statue of a white guy you’re tearing down was probably a jerk. I strongly doubt rigorous intellectual debate was had before either of these statues were torn down. (On reading more about Col. Hans Christian Heg, I actually think he might have been pretty down with a bunch of black people rising up to assert their freedom to not be systemically oppressed by toppling a statue of him, but that’s completely beside the point).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unprovoked physical violence is wrong. That Sen. Tim Carpenter was attacked is a major mistake and a complete travesty. I think assault is wrong, I’ve watched the video he took, and I think he was attacked out of the blue. I hope the perpetrators are tried appropriately. I look forward to learning more about this incident and potentially changing my mind about it, but the video evidence looked damning to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the large number of (and attention towards) counter-protestors showing up and inciting violence at peaceful demonstrations, I am not surprised that a group of protestors who see a white guy standing away from the crowd, near a vehicle, was seen as a potential threat. More generally, I am not surprised that protestors view white folks (particularly men) on the fringes of the protest with suspicion. Unprovoked physical violence is wrong, AND I see why it happened, AND that does not excuse it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may hear the phrase “tone policing,” which is defined as a personal attack anti-debate tactic in which one criticises the perceived emotion or presentation of the debater’s arguments instead of the content of the arguments presented. Some counters to this include “it’s not white folks place to tell POC how to react to oppression” or “it’s distracting from the fact that we are demonstrating against inequality.” To be honest, I disagree with the former. I do not believe we should break out the guillotine. I do believe we should give people a chance to educate themselves, and recognize the role we have all played in ongoing oppression. I do believe everyone should get a chance to make it right, and therefore, I can imagine (&lt;em&gt;but have not seen&lt;/em&gt;) tactics that one could call “protest” or “reform” but which fundamentally go against my personal philosophy of non-violence. To me, this mentally lands near my fundamental opposition to the death penalty, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the second argument holds a lot of weight. To me, the simplest response to tone-policing is just my opinion: you should not be more concerned with how people are protesting than you are about what they’re protesting. This is NOT TRUE in the general case. In THIS case, people are not systematically going out and attacking randos who disagree with them; they are gathering peacefully AND property destruction occurs (re: above: I don’t think we can definitely say whether or not or to what degree protestors themselves are responsible for property destruction). And in THIS case people are protesting for their right to not be systemically disenfranchised, which includes feeling safe in the presence of police, but also goes beyond that to address wider racial societal issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these things taken together, what I see is an incredibly blurry picture. I do not for a second believe that the movement would be this big, that we would be talking MINIMALLY about sweeping police reform (if not entirely new models of community safety), that so many white folks would be educating themselves on the history of systemic racism and how best to dismantle it, if there were no “riots.” We learned about these protests from the media, from viral videos. From the arguments about it and the discussions and the accusations flying from both sides. Yes, peoples lives and livelihoods have been destroyed. That’s exactly what’s gotten us talking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every single person would like if this were not the case. Every protestor would love if police were already held accountable for their actions, and that they had learned about systemic disenfranchisement more holistically and earlier. I wish that voter suppression wasn’t a thing and that the US instituted gun control and that militarised police were such a foreign concept that they weren’t even in conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish the US didn’t stack the cards against black folks from the very start and that everyone had equal access to clean water and higher education and financial opportunity. Of course, I wish that were already the case. I wish that it had been this way from the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we all wish that things were different. We all wish violence could be avoided. Nobody likes going out and putting their bodies and lives on the line for justice, so we have to ask ourselves, why are people doing it? Either all these protestors are evil, no-good, taking-advantage-of-distraction, mal-intentioned hooligans, or they’re between a rock and a hard place. If we don’t believe all these hundreds of thousands of people are just riotous thugs, then we must ask ourselves: why is this happening?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The punchline: it would be great if violence were never the answer, but in practice property destruction and money are how to make people listen and care to the powerless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where do we draw the line at “justifiable violence?” I have no flippin’ clue. But I do know that my previous answer of “violence is NEVER justified” was informed by entire life of never experiencing physical violence from those who were meant to protect me. I still believe unprovoked violence against people is wrong, and my research and media bubble both suggest that’s also the zeitgeist of the movement as well. But over the last weeks, my view on property destruction has changed. I don’t have all the answers, but I think it’s pretty undeniable that without property destruction, this movement would have died just like it has every other time we’ve heard about the death of an unarmed black man begging for their life. It sucks that we need property destruction to get people to care (enough to take action) about systemic violence against black people, but given that we do, my personal calculation is that it’s a fair trade-off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links:
Assault of Tim Carpenter: https://www.cnn.com/…/madison-arrest…/index.html
Data on police violence can be found here: https://mappingpoliceviolence.org/nationaltrends
Link for MLK article: https://time.com/519…/10-historians-martin-luther-king-jr/
Baltimore riots I just used wikipedia (but I checked the sources): https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2015_Baltimore_protests…
Suffragettes: https://www.theguardian.com/…/the-role-of-violence-in…
Property destruction and instigating change: https://www.newyorker.com/…/how-violent-protests-change…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Carolyn Saund</name><email>carolyn.saund@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Black Lives Matter" /><category term="political violence" /><category term="protest" /><summary type="html">For Folks who think Racism exists and needs to be dealt with, But Violence Is Never The Answer. Longest so far, and with the fewest concrete sources. I can’t find many good statistics.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">‘All Lives Matter’</title><link href="https://csaund.github.io/blog/equity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="'All Lives Matter'" /><published>2020-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://csaund.github.io/blog/blog-post-19</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://csaund.github.io/blog/equity/">&lt;p&gt;For people who think the police are thugs who are out of control, and also think “All Lives Matter.”
The ground rules from before still apply. We are friends. I respect you, and you respect me at least enough to read this post. I am happy to engage either publicly or privately, and will listen with an open mind as I hope you do to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll come out and say this now: Yes, All Lives Matter. In the strictest sense, you are correct. The fact that All Lives Matter is unalienable and we all must stand unflinching in the truth that, indeed, All Lives Matter. So, why are you being called a bigot or racist for simply saying what we all agree with: that all lives matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are NOT racist for thinking “all lives matter.” It is true that the life of every person who has been innocently murdered or unjustly arrested, matters. It is true that you may be completely agnostic to people’s race — that you are kind to and treat everyone as individuals. That you, yourself, are not racist, and would NEVER treat somebody differently because of their race. Because of these things, you think that “All lives matter” is the correct thing to say, because it is true. And it hurts to be called “racist” when you have spent your whole life striving to treat individuals equally. What gives?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to try to break down why, in the current political context, the truth that “all lives matter” rings pretty tone-deaf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saying things like “I do not treat people differently because of their race” is a variant of “I don’t see race” or “I treat everybody equally.” This invokes an idea of Exceptionalism (specifically, White Exceptionalism). When these things are said, it wilfully refuses to acknowledge that every white person has responsibility and accountability for racism. By excluding yourself from being “racist,” you excuse yourself from your responsibility and accountability for racism. While this responsibility is personal (the one which you already practice by not actively being a dick towards people of other races), it is also global. As a white person, you have abilities that BIPOC do not: your voice is heard at PTA meetings, on city councils, and by racists. Similar to how you may have seen protestors protect each other by creating “white shields” (where white people move to the front of protests, between black folks and police), white people must be leading the charge for equal treatment because the fact of the matter is we are, demonstrably, not there yet. YOU don’t treat people differently because of their race, but that’s not an excuse, because society DOES treat people differently because of their race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is close, also, to the idea of “color blindness,” which is the idea that because you treat everybody equally, everybody gets a fair shot with you, so they get a fair shot with the world. While it can be great that you, personally, evaluate people as individuals, this ignores the fact that BIPOC do not get fair treatment in the world at large. Because of this, you (not racist) may “see” problematic behavior disproportionately by BIPOC. You may see crime statistics, or untreated mental illness, or “uncivilised” or “rude” behaviour and not associate the systemic obstacles to success that others face, and while you do not treat individuals differently because of their race, you can’t help but notice it’s always X folks actin’ this way. By saying that because you yourself are not racist you treat everybody equally, you excuse yourself from judging individuals through the inherently racial lens that society imposes on us. It is NOT your fault that that lens exists, but it is your problem. If you want to get back to judging people as individuals, you have to use that privilege we just talked about to help society at large judge people as individuals, too. You have to use the underlying white supremacy in society to defeat the white supremacy in society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This touches on the idea of “White guilt.” I’m going to be completely honest and I say I have no idea what the zeitgeist is saying about white guilt right now, but I can tell you that white guilt is weaponised often: “I didn’t own slaves, I don’t benefit off the backs of black people, why should I feel guilty for something my ancestors did?” My answer, as a white person, is: you shouldn’t feel guilty, but you should sure as hell recognise the ways that you benefit from the system being set up for you to succeed NOT because it’s been easy for you, but because it’s been even harder for others. Allyship isn’t about feelings of guilt and atonement, but about being motivated by justice: It is simply, viscerally wrong that other people do not get the same treatment as I do because of the color of their skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, saying “All Lives Matter, because what about the other people who are murdered? What about how dangerous it is to be a cop?” is a classic distraction (Whataboutery?) which seeks to downplay the situation at hand. Yes, other people are harmed too. Yes, lifetime prison sentences are abhorrent. Yes, mental health is medically neglected. This is bad. AND it is not the issue at hand, which is that BIPOC people are subject to disproportionate violence and discrimination by police (and throughout other systems!) in the US and UK.  In the words of my girl Saoirse Ronan in Lady Bird, “different things can be sad.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that I haven’t seen explicitly in my circles but I think is worth a mention is the common theme that “I don’t want to argue, this is my opinion,” or “You’re entitled to your opinion, I’m entitled to mine.” This is an example of refusing to engage in debate and potentially acknowledge problematic behaviours, and instead getting defensive in such a way that shuts out all other opinions. Rather than reflect on your actions of beliefs, this focuses the conversation on YOUR feelings and YOUR hurt, not the facts and hands or the reasons behind your beliefs (which are likely the focal point of the conversation, anyway). This shuts down discussion and says “I am not open to learning things that may hurt my feelings.” This is also called “White fragility.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to point out, this is extremely different from “can we not talk about this right now?” or “I am not ready for this discussion.” It is ok to be emotionally exhausted, mentally out-of-breath, or just straight up too tired to take things in. Changing beliefs is EXHAUSTING. It is HARD. It cannot be done quickly. Even just listening to people you love saying things that are contrary to your beliefs can be painful, and it is ok to acknowledge that you are hurting, sad, tired, and can’t take more at a particular moment. You can take time to mentally prepare for these conversations, and only engage in them when you are ready to genuinely listen with an open heart. The key here is: you can’t put this off forever. You must acknowledge that at some point, you must have this reckoning, either with yourself or your loved ones. You can delay, but it can be helpful to say “let’s talk about this next time,” and recognise the mental effort you will have preparing for a Difficult Conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a more personal note, I recognise that it can hurt to hear a lot of new, contextually-hateful or call-out language denoted around race. “White fragility,” “white guilt,” “white supremacy,” “white exceptionalism,” — it is really difficult to be pinned to these phrases despite not having a personal relationship with them, especially when they’re used to tell someone, essentially, that they’re ignorant or mis-informed. However, I think a majority of white people that I reach will probably share my experience that I’ve never had a “racial” identity before (I do have an American “cultural” identity, but that’s a whole ‘nother story). I’ve never had to. White has been the default. I’ve never been White-American, just American. Something that has helped me start to shed my defensiveness has been embracing my racial identity and the unique aspects of it, and acknowledging and sort-of internally “celebrating” my whiteness, insofar as I recognise the enormous power it gives me in certain situations, and it is an aspect of my life around which I can now learn to “control,” (I can’t change the color of my skin, but I can wield it and STFU when it’s inappropriate to say anything).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum it up: you’re not a racist for believing that “all lives matter.” They do. And right now, we have to rally around the lives under threat, so that all lives can continue mattering. All lives matter equally, so right now, we have to step up and make the world around us reflect that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“All lives matter,” but that is totally not the point. Black lives matter. Let’s start acting like it. “All lives matter” is technically true, but saying that completely erases the narrative of what we’re fighting for, which is black lives, and, more generally, racial equality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Carolyn Saund</name><email>carolyn.saund@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Black Lives Matter" /><category term="racial equality" /><category term="All Lives Matter" /><summary type="html">For people who think the police are thugs who are out of control, and also think “All Lives Matter.” The ground rules from before still apply. We are friends. I respect you, and you respect me at least enough to read this post. I am happy to engage either publicly or privately, and will listen with an open mind as I hope you do to me.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tear Down The Statues</title><link href="https://csaund.github.io/blog/statues/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tear Down The Statues" /><published>2020-06-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://csaund.github.io/blog/blog-post-20</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://csaund.github.io/blog/statues/">&lt;p&gt;White folks who don’t like police brutality AND also don’t like tearing down statues: an earnest rebuttal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ground rules: If you are reading this then you know me, I know you, and we are friends (in the American sense of the word ❤ ). You must know that I do and will continue to respect you, and I am open to hearing rebuttals and disagreements, and I will not make assumptions about you, your values, or your history. If you want to engage, I will listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of older white folks have opened up to me recently on their feelings on the statues. “Why do they have to tear down the statues?” “Doesn’t this symbolize a steep turning point towards violence?” “How will we remember the terrible things that have happened without the statues?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These types of questions and feelings are, in my opinion, a way of saying “I feel threatened by this.” For whatever reason. Some may feel threatened because they think their way of life will be erased, because the history of their nation is under attack, or because this could be a stepping stone towards future violence. I hope to dispel those arguments and show that I am open to conversation on the matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(1) History is not remembered by monuments, it is memorialised by monuments. Statues are rewards for doing something good, for a community or for a country. Statues are also a signal to a township “this is what we, as a community, value.” Some may be particularly aesthetic or realistic, some abstract interpretations, but they are indisputably publicly available signals. By erecting statues that glorify and memorialize extremely painful moments in some folks collective histories, without their consent and often with conscientious and continuous objection, society continues to erase the voices of marginalized groups. Statues of slavers signal that we, as a country, have NOT grappled with the sins of our past, and choose to keep silent the voices that have called continuously to remove these monuments. If we had, surely we would take down these monuments to a shameful history in favour of more peaceful and optimistic beacons of the future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(2) How much history have you learned by reading plaques on statues? How much of it painted the figure in a negative light? How much do you think the average person has learned from statues? We learn history from textbooks and school curriculum, not monuments. Monuments are the ultimate virtue-signal, and having statues of famous slavers and leaders of genocide indicates that we STILL think “well, the good outweighed the bad,” and forget the lives of hundreds of thousands of people who died at their hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(2b) Are we losing our collective history by re-framing the founding of the US with a racial lens? This I doubt very much. I think telling the true and fuller story of the founding of the US, with the warts of slavery and the continuous progression towards equal rights (towards which we still strive) does not cheapen the doctrine of hope and a promise of prosperity of the US. On the contrary, I think recognising our shared, flawed history and the struggle towards amending the system to be genuinely fair adds a level of self-awareness and maturity to the US that I have never felt or seen. I feel more patriotic now, seeing my fellow countrymen rise up NOT to destroy and remove everyone in power, but to review the status quo and question foundational principles in order to build something better, for everyone. It is undeniably true that BIPoC and Women’s voices (as well as poor white folks!) were actively excluded from our founding documents. I don’t think it tears down the idea of the American dream to recognise this fact and attempt to amend our doctrines to include more marginalised perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Western society IS a trajectory. I believe this movement and moment in history is a positive turn in which we begin to grapple with a painful past and move forward together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(3) By tearing down these statues and “erasing history,” are we careening towards a violent revolution? In my opinion, no, absolutely not. Comparing the tearing down of statues to violent revolutions such as Nazi Germany or the Khmer Rouge, who tore down and killed mercilessly to pave way for a new future, likens BLM to these abhorrent groups. It almost seems to purposely turn a blind eye to the fact that BLM fights for equal rights, equal treatment, the right to exist, while Adolf Hitler and Pol Pot wanted to extinguish particular groups. BLM has NEVER called for violence against other humans, because it’s against the platform that we fight for: that all humans have a right to exist on an equal playing field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, you will never see statues of Nazis or Khmer Rouge sitting out in town squares. Places of remembrance are large, extremely informative (museums or areas (killing fields, Auschwitz) that are explicitly for learning and mourning). They are somber and appropriately memorialise genocide, in that they indisputably profess a shared shame or helplessness at the hands of evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may wonder “but why should I feel ashamed for something I didn’t do [, slavery]?” I will address White Guilt in a future post. But the short answer is: you shouldn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(3b) While some may not appreciate the imagery of beheading statues of white men, I am not aware of any BLM representatives (or even any far-left activists?) who have EVER called for any level of violence against other humans. Perhaps controversial, but I would still call a protest in which statues are torn down “peaceful,” because no humans were harmed and really, no individuals were displaced. I will cover “peaceful protests vs. riots” in another post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Carolyn Saund</name><email>carolyn.saund@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Black Lives Matter" /><category term="racial equality" /><category term="All Lives Matter" /><summary type="html">White folks who don’t like police brutality AND also don’t like tearing down statues: an earnest rebuttal.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Im Having Fun And You Cant Stop Me</title><link href="https://csaund.github.io/blog/happiness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Im Having Fun And You Cant Stop Me" /><published>2019-08-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://csaund.github.io/blog/blog-post-14</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://csaund.github.io/blog/happiness/">&lt;p&gt;In the past, I’ve been accused of having “too much fun,” at work. That it “looks like I don’t do anything,” and I’m “always off away from the lab.” I post “too many photos of having fun,” and am generally far too cheery when folks ask me how I’m doing. Apparently, “fantastic!” and “living the dream!” are inappropriate responses to this question. It’s as if having fun, enjoying my lab, loving the fact that my work is the bomb-diggity, means that I can’t possibly be doing any real work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this really grinds my gears, because I actively try to cultivate a persona that runs counter to the absurd notion that happiness and productivity are somehow mutually exclusive. Here are some hard truths of my life of which I’m frankly not ashamed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;(1) Grad School Isn't Miserable&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and I’m tired of everyone acting like it is. I get that this varies a lot advisor-to-advisor and person-to-person, but frankly it’s pretty damn awesome for me. When people say “oh well you just started,” or “just wait it gets horrible,” I want to yell. What kind of attitude is that? Why would I embark on this journey with that sort of endorsement? What do you, fellow grad student, gain from telling me about my future misery? Why are you so fussed when I refuse to commiserate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked for three years before coming back to grad school, and I think that’s made all the difference for me. I spent a lot of time honing what I was truly interested in, exploring different research avenues and possibilities, and deciding what programs were and were not right for me. I gained valuable work skills such as managing long-term projects and working with diverse teams and doing my laundry even though I just worked for 14 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, mostly, I prepped for the PhD. I read the books and did my homework on what a PhD means and does not mean, I talked to friends and friends-of-friends, and I feel like I jumped in clear-eyed about what’s to come. I’ll joke about my self-perceived ability and tangling up my self-worth with my scientific achievements, but you will never catch me without a glint in my eye that I get to do this every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am having fun, and you can’t stop me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;(2) I'm Most Productive When I'm Happiest&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and honestly, you probably are, too. Because, as it turns out, happy people are more productive. I mean, for the love of god, look at the data! I don’t need to read these to tell you why I am more productive when I’m happy, cause I just feel it for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am extremely socially externally motivated, so if I’m doing work for someone I respect and I feel supports me, I am extremely interested in doing a lot for that person. I am also very excited to come into a lab where I like and respect the people around me. As it turns out, having fun with people promotes bonding, and consequently, respecting your lab mates. So, when we, as a lab, head off on a weekend trip, or Thursday-night-pints, or lab lunches (personally funded), all it shows is we genuinely enjoy spending time with each other. Is this a good time for #sorrynotsorry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, when I am unhappy, almost nothing motivates me. I am extremely fortunate to be in consistently good-to-very-good mental health, cause if that were not the case I would get nothing done. On the rare occasion I’m feeling blue, I can barely open an email let alone do my actual job. I accomplish things because I feel supported, encouraged, and empowered to pursue my own intellectual development, under the guidance of my advisor, my lab, and my department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I Hate the Capitalist Dystopia in which Happiness and Productivity are Mutually Exclusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;(3) Grad School Is a Multi-Faceted Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, the majority of my time at work isn’t spent doing “science,” but instead the vast amount of other things that fall under the job description of PhD Student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On any given day I may be asked to: analyze data, write a paper, apply for workshops and grants, organize conferences, run trainings, present at metascience meetings, run department social media, organize grad student social events, organize lab social events, brainstorm and design and pilot new experiments, run participants, evangelize the field, work on student or department committees, speak to the public about the research, write for a public-facing journal or blog, or any number of the other myriad things that academia kind of just takes for granted that grad students just do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I love that! One of my favorite things about my work is how varied it is from day to day. I love the variety, and I love broadcasting that variety, too. I’m excited to share that being a “scientist,” isn’t a just solitary experience crunching numbers and fretting about equations and code that doesn’t compile, but about being a part of a scientific community. I love variety, I love collaboration, and I love showing people the great deal of fun associated with those things. Because…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;(4) Science is for Everyone&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and I want to make that clear. “Science,” and “Academia,” should be accessible to everybody who wants in, and who wants those things when they’re branded as soul-sucking wastes of time? I am proud to cultivate the persona of the happy scientist, who’s genuinely excited by her research, and absolutely jazzed every single day to work on HUMAN SOCIAL COGNITION, LIKE BUT ALSO THERE ARE ROBOTS!?!?!?! Like, whaaaaaaaat!? That IS awesome and I’m not about to tell you it isn’t!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I’m gonna portray that happiness and show you a face of science you might not be used to. I’m going to be unabashedly gleeful, unashamedly proud of my failures and successes, shamelessly curious, brazenly animated about the “work,” that I do every day, and tirelessly, relentlessly, continuously positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Don't temper happiness to fit society's idea of productivity.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let work speak for itself. Write papers, run experiments, organize guest speakers, present to the department, be a TA, build social bonds, evangelize the school, do the dang job, then talk to me about productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, just know it’s cool to be happy while you work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Carolyn Saund</name><email>carolyn.saund@gmail.com</email></author><category term="happiness" /><category term="academia" /><category term="productivity" /><summary type="html">In the past, I’ve been accused of having “too much fun,” at work. That it “looks like I don’t do anything,” and I’m “always off away from the lab.” I post “too many photos of having fun,” and am generally far too cheery when folks ask me how I’m doing. Apparently, “fantastic!” and “living the dream!” are inappropriate responses to this question. It’s as if having fun, enjoying my lab, loving the fact that my work is the bomb-diggity, means that I can’t possibly be doing any real work.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Hype is Real, but the Tech is Not.</title><link href="https://csaund.github.io/blog/tech_hype" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Hype is Real, but the Tech is Not." /><published>2019-07-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://csaund.github.io/blog/blog-post-13</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://csaund.github.io/blog/tech_hype">&lt;p&gt;Human-Computer interaction is hard, but our technological interfaces have improved over time. From terminal commands to touchpads, and text to voice interfaces, consumer electronics industries understand that ease-of-use is of the utmost importance to customers. The ultimate evolution of this idea is a frictionless Brain-Computer Interface (BCI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These interfaces envisage a seductively convenient future: Machines that turn ideas to fully formed papers, gadgets that download memories so you never forget memories so you never forget, implanted devices for a wide array of medical conditions. With such tremendous possibility to break into the tech marketplace, a number of companies are working to make this dream a reality, and they’re getting lots of money for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While French gaming company NextMind tries to let users control video games with their $5M disclosed funding, medical device companies like Kernel and MindMaze have raised upwards of $100M to realize dreams of memory extension and neurorehabilitation through Neural Interfaces. Californian NeuroPace has gotten over $200M for their implant that responds to neurological activity. And, despite being intensely secretive, NeuraLink has raised over $27M for claiming to one day provide “super-human cognition.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These companies make assertions about their products based on sound research. Scientists showed humans are able to control interfaces on screens and even prosthetics using only their mind as early as 1991. Neurostimulation has shown to have profound effects on the ability to perceive empathy and boost cognition. We have even visualized memories based solely on brain activity. This shows significant scientific progress in the field of BCI, but is that enough for these companies to succeed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going from a Proof-of-Concept to a product is a perilous journey. Looking at the field of social robotics, there are troubling comparisons, as demonstrated by the rise and fall of Jibo, Aido, Miro, Anki, and all your other two-syllable-end-vowel robotics companies. These companies were based on research from MIT, Oxford, and Harvard that said social robots are socially desirable and medically helpful. They managed to raise staggering amounts of money, often in the realm of $100M or more. They were run by charismatic, successful serial-entrepreneurs. But ultimately, these robotics companies were built on future bets founded on the premise that we have technologies which we just do not yet have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magic of BCI, like that of robots, captures the popular imagination. It’s important that someone dreams big and looks to the future – pulls the popular zeitgeist towards the presently-impossible but theoretically-plausible. Going from unimaginable to imagined is no small feat, and these companies are filling and important role in that regard. But, as usual when non-experts are confronted with dramatic future visions, things are blown out of proportion too quickly. While BCIs show intriguing potential to transform future interactions with technology, until any company successfully brings a BCI product to market that consumers can purchase off-the-shelf, assertions of their immediate impact should be met with scepticism. This article in full together with references can be found at: https://www.bna.org.uk/publications/ bright-brains/bb-online/.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Carolyn Saund</name><email>carolyn.saund@gmail.com</email></author><category term="tech" /><category term="software" /><category term="hype" /><summary type="html">Human-Computer interaction is hard, but our technological interfaces have improved over time. From terminal commands to touchpads, and text to voice interfaces, consumer electronics industries understand that ease-of-use is of the utmost importance to customers. The ultimate evolution of this idea is a frictionless Brain-Computer Interface (BCI).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Report Responsibly</title><link href="https://csaund.github.io/posts/2019/02/please-report-responsibly/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Report Responsibly" /><published>2019-03-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-03-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://csaund.github.io/posts/2019/02/blog-post-12</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://csaund.github.io/posts/2019/02/please-report-responsibly/">&lt;p&gt;How can we, as scientists, do better to inform the public of what we’re actually doing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“IMMORTALITY POSSIBLE? World’s’s first human head transplant successfully carried out,”
reads the headline of one of the top search results for “head transplant” (2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This headline is a particularly egregious example of how research in neuroscience and psychology often leads the
general public to extrapolate wildly about the nature and possibilities of humanity. It is absolutely
necessary that we, as a cohesive scientific community, ensure the public understands what we
are and are not doing – what is and is not currently possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people only read about 20% of the contents of an online article (1). While the goal of an
online journal is to get the most clicks on their articles, we need to ensure that the scientific
findings and interpretations being transmitted are accurate and not debased. Here are a few
excellent ways for scientists to convey their findings and debunk myths about their research to
the general public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get involved in public outreach campaigns. In order to control the message being delivered,
researchers can be the ones who start conversations. When we initiate public discussions about
our research topics, we can manage misconceptions directly with the people we are
communicating with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Review the university press release. Although we cannot directly control how media outlets
publish our studies, we can ensure the source-of-truth of any scientific reporting is accurate.
Additionally, we often have more power within our own universities to correct errors or
misleading phrasing than with general consumer publications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create and publish guides for readers. We can write up FAQs about our research that are
easily understandable, and publish them in public domains, like researchers from
Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) did with their important study investigating mortality
after Hurricane Maria in Puerto Rico (3). Filtering out jargon helps the general public gain an
intuition for what the findings mean, and how they can or cannot be interpreted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, as scientists, are in extremely powerful positions as experts in our domains. Consequently,
we must also uphold our duty to ensure findings are properly reported, de-sensationalized, and
understood by a broad audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References
Austin, J. (2017). IMMORTALITY POSSIBLE? Worlds first human head transplant successfully
carried out. Express. https://www.express.co.uk/news/science/880926/Human-head-transplant-
world-s-first-successful-corpse-Sergio-Canavero [Accessed 17 October 2018]
Weinreich H, Obendorf H, Herder H, and Mayer M (2018) Not Quite the Average: An Empirical
Study of Web Use , ACM Transactions on the Web, vol. 2, no. 1, article #5 [Accessed 13
October 2018]
Kiang, M (2018) Hurricane Maria Mortality Study FAQ, on Github https://github.com/c2-
d2/pr_mort_official/blob/master/misc/faq.md [Accessed 15 October 2018]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Carolyn Saund</name><email>carolyn.saund@gmail.com</email></author><category term="science" /><category term="academia" /><category term="report" /><category term="presscoverage" /><summary type="html">How can we, as scientists, do better to inform the public of what we’re actually doing?</summary></entry></feed>